

MANJEET KUMAR

Ph.D.

@ manjeetbhatia83@gmail.com

J +91-7869442921

Kangra, (H.P.) India

in Manjeet Bhatia

Manjeetkb

STRENGTHS

Computational Chemistry/DFT Software

Quantum Espresso

SIESTA & TranSIESTA

Gaussian

ATK-Virtual Nano lab

MD Simulations

MBN Explorer

DL Poly

TECHNICAL

OS & Scientific software

Window Linux

OriginLab **MTFX**

HTML CSS Django

HPC experience

CINECA HPC systems

ISCRA class C project

Programming languages

Shell Scripting

Python numpy

pandas scipy

Matplotlib

C/C++ (basic)

Fortran (basic)

Machine Learning

Linear regression

Logistic regression

Gaussian Process

Scikit learn

MOTIVATION

An enthusiastic, adaptive and fast-learning person with a broad and acute interest in condensed matter physics and DFT based calculations. I particularly enjoy working and collaborating with researchers from different disciplines to develop new skills and solve new challenges.

EXPERIENCE

Research Associate | University of Hyderabad, Hyderabad.

Mar 2022 - May 2022

Hvderabad, India.

• Project: Developing an artificial intelligence-based algorithm for exploring surface reaction mechanisms.

Junior Research Fellow | ABV-IIITM, Gwalior.

Mar 2016 - Oct 2017

Gwalior, India.

- Project: Ab-initio investigation of structural and electronic properties of Zn (Cd)-VI nanowires.
- Pressure induced phase transitions in nanostructures.
- Electronic, optical and magnetic properties of materials.

Project Fellow | ISSC, University of Pune.

a Aug 2014 - Dec 2014

Pune, India.

- Project: First principles investigations of conductance in photo catalytic materials.
- Optimization of fullerene-porphyrin system.
- Ab-initio Calculations on fullerene-porphyrin system.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Physics | Department of Physics, University of Milan.

Nov 2017 - Dec 2020

Milan, Italy.

- Thesis Title: Ab-initio Calculation of the Rates of the Reactions between Volatile Organic Compounds in Wine and Cations for Mass Spectrometry.
- Thesis Supervisor: Prof. Nicola Manini.

M.Phil. Physics | Department of Physics, Pondicherry University.

Aug 2011 - Sep 2013

Pondicherry, India.

- Thesis Title: Electronic transport through ferroelectric barrier by using density functional theory calculations.
- Thesis Supervisor: Dr. Gangineni Ramesh Babu.

M.Sc. Physics (Hons.) | Department of Physics, Punjab University.

a Aug 2006 - Aug 2008

Chandigarh, India.

SVM KNN

Decision tree

Random forest

Naive Bayes

K-means (Keras

Neural network

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Condensed Matter Physics

Ab initio Calculations

Electronic Structure Methods

Computational Chemistry

Surface Reactions

Reaction Kinetics

Gas-phase Ion Chemistry

Transport Properties

LANGUAGES

Hindi: Native

English: Professional

Italian: Beginner

REFERENCES

Prof. Nicola Manini

Department of Physics, University of Milan, Via Giovanni Celoria, 16, 20133 Milano MI, ITALY.

@ nicola.manini@unimi.it

J +39 02 50317355

Dr. Franco Biasioli

Department of Food Quality and Nutrition, Research and Innovation Center, Fondazione Edmund Mach, 38010 San Michele all'Adige, TN, Italy.

@ franco.biasioli@fmach.it
J +39 0461 615 187

Prof. Luca Cappellin

Disc

Dipartimento di Scienze Chimiche, Universita Degli Studi di Padova, Via Marzolo 1, 35121, Padua, Italy. • Subjects: Quantum Mechanics, Classical Mechanics, Statistical, Electronics, Mathematical Physics, Electrodynamics, Nuclear Physics, Particle Physics.

PGDCA | CEDTI, New Delhi.

Aug 2004 - Sep 2005

• Dharamshala, India.

 Subjects: Personal Computer System, Business System, System Analysis & Design, Programming in C/C++, Programming in VB, SQL Server, Computer Graphics & Multimedia, and Internet Programming Tools.

B.Sc. | Himachal Pradesh University, India.

Jul 2001 - June 2004

Dharamshala, India.

• Subjects: Physics, Chemistry, Mathematics.

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-reviewed

- 1. **Manjeet Bhatia**, Franco Biasioli, Luca Cappellin and Kulvinder Singh, A Quantum-chemical Evaluation of Gas-Phase Proton Affinity, Ionization Energy and Reactivity Parameters for Wine Volatiles, to be submitted in 'Molecules'.
- 2. Manjeet Bhatia, Nicola Manini, Franco Biasioli, Luca Cappellin, Calculated Rate Coefficients Between CI-MS Reagent Ions and Organosulfur Compounds Causing Food Taints and Off-flavours, *International Journal of Mass Spectrometry*, 478, 116860 2022. (IF 1.98)
- 3. **Manjeet Bhatia**, Nicola Manini, Franco Biasioli, Luca Cappellin, Theoretical Investigation of Charge Transfer from NO⁺ and O₂⁺ Ions to Wine-Related Volatile Compounds for Mass Spectrometry, *Journal of the American Society for Mass Spectrometry*, 33, 2, 251-264 2022. (**IF 3.11**)
- 4. **Manjeet Bhatia**, Franco Biasioli, Luca Cappellin, Paolo Piseri, Nicola Manini, Abinitio calculation of the proton transfer reaction rate coefficients to volatile organic compounds related to cork-taint in wine, *Journal of Mass Spectrometry*, 55(11), e4592, 2020. (**IF 1.98**)
- 5. Manjeet Bhatia, Uma Shankar Sharma, Anurag Srivastava, Chromium Influenced High Magnetic Moment and Half-Metallic Nature of GaN Nanotube, *Journal of Nanoscience and Nanotechnology*, Volume 19, Number 7 2019. (IF 1.35)
- 6. **Manjeet Bhatia**, Md. Shahzad Khan and Anurag Srivastava, Pressure induced phase transition in CdTe nanowire: A DFT study, AIP Conference Proceedings, 1953, 040033 (2018).
- 7. Md. Shahzad Khan, **Manjeet Bhatia** and Anurag Srivastava, Structural and electronic properties of rectangular CdTe nanowire: A DFT study, AIP Conference Proceedings, 1953, 040136 (2018).
- 8. **Manjeet Bhatia** and Anurag Srivastava, Band gap and magnetic moment of Ga1-xCrxN, AIP Conference Proceedings, 1832, 090045 (2017).
- 9. **Manjeet K. Bhatia** and G.Ramesh Babu, Electronic transport across a layered structure of Fe/ β -poly vinylidene fluoride/Fe using DFT calculations, *Journal of Computational Electronics volume* 13, pages 613–619 2014. (**IF 1.81**)

PRESENTATIONS/POSTERS

- 1. Poster Presentation in TUMIEE Training School, 23 Sep-04 Oct 2019, Rethymno, Crete, Greece.
- 2. Poster Presentation in Summer School on Advanced Materials and Molecular Modelling, 16 Sep-20 Sep 2019, J. Stefan Institute, Ljubljana, Slovenia.
- 3. Poster Presentation in 4th International Conference on Nanoscience and Technology (ICONN 2017), SRM University, Kattankulathur-603203, Chennai, India.
- 4. Poster Presentation in 61st DAE Solid State Physics Symposium (DAE-SSPS December 26-30, 2016), KIIT University, Bhubaneswar, India.



Prof. Paolo Piseri

 Department of Physics, University of Milan, Via Giovanni Celoria, 16, 20133 Milano MI, ITALY.

paolo.piseri@unimi.it **J** +39 02503 17357

- 5. Poster Presentation in 4th International e-workshop on computational condensed matter physics (IWCCMP-2016), November 18-20, 2016, ABV-IIITM, Gwalior, India.
- 6. Poster presentation, 27th PSSI National Symposium on Plasma Science and Technology, December 2012, Pondicherry University, India.

SCHOOLS/WORKSHOPS

GAUSSIAN Workshop | 🌐

- **i** 20 Jan 2020 24 Jan 2020
- Hyderabad, India.
- Introduction to Gaussian: Theory and Practice.

COST-TS-ECOST Training School | 🏶

- **2** 23 Sep 2019 04 Oct 2019
- Rethymno, Crete, Greece.
- COST Action 17126 TUMIEE Training School.

QUANTUM ESPRESSO Summer School | •

- iii 16 Sep 2019 20 Sep 2019
- JSI, Ljubljana, Slovenia.
- QUANTUM ESPRESSO Summer School on Advanced Materials and Molecular Modelling.

ICONN 2017 | 🌐



- **i** 09 Aug 2017 11 Aug 2017
- SRM University, Chennai.
- 4th International Conference on Nanoscience and Technology.

DAE-SSPS | 🏶

- **26** Dec 2016 30 Dec 2016
- KIIT University, Bhubaneswar.
- 61st DAE Solid State Physics Symposium.

IWCCMP | 🏶



- **18** Nov 2016 20 Nov 2016
- ABV-IIITM, Gwalior.
- 4th International e-workshop on Computational Condensed Matter Physics.

PSSI National Symposium | •



- 10 Dec 2012 13 Dec 2012
- Pondicherry University, Pondicherry.
- 27th PSSI National Symposium on Plasma Science and Technology.

PRIZE & AWARDS

- COST Action CA17126 Trainee Grant €1200, ECOST Association.
- UGC Scholarship for M.Phil. €500, India.
- Higher Secondary Scholarship, €250, India.